Inventory of the Alexander Harrison Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Alexander Harrison papers
1945-1985
bulk, 1978-1985
84063
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 3 envelopes (1.8 linear feet)
Sound recordings and written summaries of interviews, other writings, and photographs relating to the role of the Organisation Armée Secrète (OAS) in the Algerian war for independence and the attempted coup against President Charles de Gaulle of France. Includes interviews with Raoul Salan, Edmond Jouhaud, Maurice Challe, and other leaders of the Organisation Armée Secrète, and the typescript of Harrison's book, Challenging de Gaulle: The O.A.S. and the Counterrevolution in Algeria, 1954-1962.
Harrison, Alexander.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. Use copies of some sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material in this collection are available for immediate access. To listen to other sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical note
American historian.
Scope and Contents note
Sound recordings and written summaries of interviews, other writings, and photographs relating to the role of the Organisation Armée Secrète (OAS) in the Algerian war for independence and the attempted coup against President Charles de Gaulle of France. Includes interviews with Raoul Salan, Edmond Jouhaud, Maurice Challe, and other leaders of the Organisation Armée Secrète, and the typescript of Harrison's book, Challenging de Gaulle: The O.A.S. and the Counterrevolution in Algeria, 1954-1962.
Challe, Maurice, 1905-1979.; Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970.; Jouhaud, Edmond Jules René, 1905-; Organisation Armée secrète.; Salan, Raoul, 1899-1984.; Africa.; Algeria--History--Revolution, 1954-1962.; Algeria.; France--History--1958-; France.; Phonotapes.
- Speeches and Writings, 1984
  - Book manuscript, "Challenging de Gaulle: The O.A.S. and the Counterrevolution in Algeria 1954-1962,", undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Speeches and writings, 1984 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Office File, 1945-1951
  - Mission to Tours (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Correspondence, 1985, undated
  - Martel, Robert, 1985 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Ramos, Jean-Pierre, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Interview Documents, 1978-1979, undated
  - List of informants, undated (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Transcripts, 1978-1979, undated
    - Andugar, François and Josué Giner, undated (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Blanchy, Jean-Loup, undated (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Blay, Germaine, undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - Crespin, Maurice, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - Dupont, Claude, undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Garcia, Alexander, undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Georgopoulous, Athanèse, undated (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Gignac, Yves, undated (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Gras, Jean-Paul, Claude Dupont, and Joseph Cabero-Borgia, undated (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Interview with various former OAS members, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Laridji, Hadj, undated (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Mancilla, Paul, undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Nocetti, Paul, undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Perez, Jean-Claude, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Ramos, Jean-Pierre, undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Rizza, Joseph Dominique, undated (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Susini, Jean-Jacques, 1978 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Walls, Norbert and Christian Moriconi, undated (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Ziano, Ian, undated (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Subject File, undated
  - Alexander Harrison collection inventory, undated (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Oral testimony, undated (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Printed Matter, 1981-1985
  - Newspaper clippings, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 2: 11)
- Memorabilia, undated
  - OAS badge (Box-folder 2: 12)
- Photographs, 1978-1984, undated (Photo file)
  - 49 color photographs of former leaders of the OAS and of sites in Algeria associated with OAS activities, 1978-1984 (Envelope A)
  - 59 color photographs of former leaders of the OAS, undated (Envelope B)
  - 20 photographs of former leaders of the OAS, undated (Envelope C)
- Sound Recordings, 1978-1979, undated (Box 3-4)
  Scope and Contents note
  Interviews conducted in France of leaders of the Organisation Armée Secrète. On compact sound cassettes. Tapes have been arranged according to the numbers given on their labels.
  - Interview with Jean-Jacques Susini, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 1)
    Recorded in Paris. The approximate length of the interview is 90 minutes.
  - Interview with Jean-Jacques Susini, 1979 October (Phonotape-cassette 2)
    Recorded in Paris. The approximate length of the interview is 45 minutes.
  - Interview with Jean-Jacques Susini, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 3A)
    Recorded in Paris. The approximate length of the interview is 30 minutes.
  - Interview with Edouard Slama, alias Dou-Dou, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 3B)
    Recorded in Toulon. The approximate length of the interview is 20 minutes.
  - Interview with Jean-Jacques Susini, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 4)
  - Interview with Jean-Jacques Susini, 1979 October (Phonotape-cassette 5)
  - Interview with Jean-Jacques Susini, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 6)
  - Interview with Jean-Jacques Susini, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 7)
  - Interview with Jean-Jacques Susini, 1979 October (Phonotape-cassette 8)
  - Interview with Jean-Jacques Susini, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 9A)
  - Interview with Jean-Marcel Zagamé, 1979 October (Phonotape-cassette 9B)
    Recorded in Paris. The approximate length of the interview is 40 minutes.
  - Interview with Jean-Jacques Susini, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 10A)
  - Interview with Maurice Challe, former Commander-in-Chief of French Forces in Algeria, former Commander-in-Chief, Allied Forces, Europe Center, Fontainebleau, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 10B)
  - Interview with Jean-Claude Perez, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 11A)
  - Interview with Maurice Challe, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 11B)
  - Interview with Jean-Claude Perez, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 12)
  - Interview with Jean-Claude Perez, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 13)
  - Interview with Jean-Claude Perez, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 14)
  - Interview with Pierre Sergent, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 15)
    Recorded in Paris. The approximate length of the interview is two hours.
  - Interview with Edmond Jouhaud, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 16A)
  - Interview with Jacques Achard, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 16B)
  - Interview with Jacques Achard, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 17)
  - Interview with Jacques Achard, 1979 October (Phonotape-cassette 18)
  - Interview with Joseph Cabero-Borgia, 1979 October (Phonotape-cassette 19)
  - Interview with Joseph Cabero-Borgia, 1979 October (Phonotape-cassette 20)
  - Interview with Robert Martel, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 21)
    Recorded in Montferrand. The approximate length of the interview is 90 minutes.
  - Interview with Robert Martel, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 22)
  - Interview with Robert Martel, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 23)
  - Interview with Robert Martel, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 24A)
    Recorded in Montferrand. The approximate length of the interview is 75 minutes.
  - Interview with Yvan Santini, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 24B)
    Recorded in Toulouse. The approximate length of the interview is 60 minutes.
  - Interview with François (Fan Fan) Leca, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 25)
    Recorded in Montpellier. The approximate length of the interview is 40 minutes.
  - Interview with François Leca, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 26)
    Recorded in Montpellier. The approximate length of the interview is 90 minutes.
  - Interview with François Leca, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 27)
    Recorded in Montpellier. The approximate length of the interview is 45 minutes.
  - Interview with François Leca, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 28)
  - Interview with Robet Tabarot, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 29)
    Recorded in Cannes. The approximate length of the interview is 45 minutes.
  - Interview with Robet Tabarot, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 30)
    Recorded in Cannes. The approximate length of the interview is 45 minutes (partially distorted).
  - Interview with Yvan Santini, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 31)
    Recorded in Toulon. The approximate length of the interview is 45 minutes.
  - Interview with André Seguin and Clément Carrasco, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 32A)
  - Interview with Pierre Montagnon, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 32B)
    Recorded in Union. The approximate length of the interview is 45 minutes.
  - Interview with Pierre Montagnon, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 33)
    Recorded in Union. The approximate length of the interview is 90 minutes.
  - Interview with Gabriel Anglade, Clément Carrasco, Pierre Demaret, and Antoine Padovani, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 34)
    Recorded in Nice.
  - Interview with Gabriel Anglade, Pierre Demaret, and Antoine Padovani, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 35)
    Recorded in Nice. The approximate length of the interview is 90 minutes.
  - Interview with Antoine Padovani, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 36A)
    Recorded in Nice. The approximate length of the interview is 22 minutes.
  - Interview with Joseph Ortiz, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 36B)
    Recorded in Toulon. The approximate length of the interview is 22 minutes.
  - Interview with Jean Gardes, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 37)
  - Interview with Jean Gardes, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 38)
  - Interview with Jean Trape, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 39)
  - Interview with Henri Dufour, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 40)
    Recorded in Marseille. The approximate length of the interview is 45 minutes.
  - Interview with Henry Dufour, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 41)
  - Interview with Armand Da Silva and François Agresta, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 42)
  - Interview with Jean-Marcel Zagamé, 1979 November (Phonotape-cassette 43A)
  - Interview with Jacques Achard, 1979 October (Phonotape-cassette 43B)
    Recorded in Paris.
  - Interview with Clément Carrasco and André Seguin, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 44)
    Recorded in Toulon. The approximate length of the interview is 1 hour and 40 minutes.
  - Interview with Raoul Louis Albin Salan, 1978 July 10 (Phonotape-cassette 45)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Use copy reference number: 84063_a_0002912
  - Interview with Georges Kopp and Auguste Arnould, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 46)
  - Interview with Auguste Arnould, 1978 July (Phonotape-cassette 47)
    Recorded in Paris. The approximate length of the interview is 60 minutes.
  - Interview with Jean-Loup Blanchy, undated (Phonotape-cassette 48)
    Recorded in Toulon. The approximate length of the interview is 50 minutes.
  - Interview with Paul (Paulot Longs Cheveux) Mancilla, undated (Phonotape-cassette 49-50)
    Recorded in the Vaucluse.The approximate length of the interview is 80 minutes.
  - Interview with Hadj Laridji, undated (Phonotape-cassette 51)
    Recorded in St. Lys (near Toulouse). The approximate length of the interview is 30 minutes.
  - Interview with Paul (Paulo) Nocetti, undated (Phonotape-cassette 52)
    Recorded in Nice. The approximate length of the interview is 45 minutes.
  - Interview with Joseph Dominique (Nani) Rizza (aka Jo le Vengeur), undated (Phonotape-cassette 53-54)
    Recorded somewhere in southeast France. The approximate length of the interview is 2 hours and 20 minutes.
  - Interview with Maurice Crespin, undated (Phonotape-cassette 55)
    Recorded in Marseille. The approximate length of the interview is 30 minutes.
  - Interview with Jean-Pierre Ramos, undated (Phonotape-cassette 56-57)
    Recorded in Marseille. The approximate length of the interview is 90 minutes.
  - Interview with Athanèse (Tassou) Georgopoulos, undated (Phonotape-cassette 58-60)
    Recorded in Cannes. The approximate length of the interview is two and a half hours.
  - Interview with Alexandre Garcia, undated (Phonotape-cassette 61)
    Recorded in the Vaucluse. The approximate length of the interview is 50 minutes.
  - Interview with Jean-Claude Perez, undated (Phonotape-cassette 62)
    Recorded in Paris. The approximate length of the interview is 50 minutes.
  - Interview with Yves Gignac, undated (Phonotape-cassette 63)
  - Interview with Claude Dupont, undated (Phonotape-cassette 64-65)
    Recorded in Paris. The approximate length of the interview is 80 minutes.
  - Interview with Jean-Paul Gras, Claude Dupont, and Joseph René (Nini) Cabero-Borgia, undated (Phonotape-cassette 66)
  - Interview with Norbert Walls and Christian Moriconi, undated (Phonotape-cassette 67-68)
    Recorded in Nice. The approximate length of the interview is 37 minutes.
  - Interview with François Andugar and Josué (Jésus de Bab-el-Oued) Giner, undated (Phonotape-cassette 69)
    Recorded in Alicante. The approximate length of the interview is 40 minutes.
  - Interview with Yan Ziano, undated (Phonotape-cassette 70-71)
  - Interview with Germaine Blay, undated (Phonotape-cassette 72-73)
    Recorded in Nice. The approximate length of the interview is 80 minutes (partially distorted).
  - Interview with Vincent Mulet and Roland Yvars, undated (Phonotape-cassette 74)